certain men of Judah and I asked them
concerning the Jews that had escaped
which were left of the captivity and
concerning Jerusalem and they said unto
me the remnant that are left in the camp
of the captivity there in the province
are in great affliction and reproach the
wall of Jerusalem also is broken down
and the gates thereof are burned with
fire and it came to pass when I heard
these words that I sat down and wept and
mourned certain days and fasted and
prayed before the God of heaven Nehemiah
is a man of God this is the time of the
medo-persian Empire and the verses we
just read describe Nehemiah asking some
of his fellow Israelites about the
condition of Jerusalem and the news that
he receives that Jerusalem is still in a
bad condition causes Nehemiah
to weep now I want to give you some
context of how Jerusalem got to this
condition in the first place
because that's going to help us to
understand what we're about to read
about this regarding this story of
Nehemiah God had brought the children of
Israel out of captivity out of Egypt
under the rulership of Pharaoh and he
brought them into what was called the
promised land and they're in the
promised land the children of Israel
were were to be obedient to God and to
put their trust in him
but the Bible records in the book of 1st
Samuel
First Samuel chapter 8 and verse five
and I will just read it in your hearing
and we'll see if we can get it up on the
screen that Samuel the priest of God has
been rejected by the children of Israel
because they want a king like the other
nations around them and the Bible says
in verse five or samuel 8 1st samuel
chapter 8 that they settled to him
behold thou art old and thy sons walk
not in thy ways now make us a king to
judge us like all the nations but the
thing displeased Samuel when they said
give us a king to judge us and Samuel
prayed unto the Lord and the Lord said
unto Samuel hearken unto the voice of
the people and all that they say unto
thee for they have not rejected thee but
they have rejected me that I should not
reign over them when the children of
Israel rejected Samuel the priest that
God had commissioned to to lead them
when they said we don't want to be ruled
of our priests we want to be ruled by a
king give us a king like all the nations
around us
God says that when they did this they in
essence rejected him
this is the beginning of the kings of
Israel the Bible tells us that the first
king was a king by the name of Saul and
in 1st Samuel Chapter 9 verse 1 the
Bible describes Saul averse to rather
the Bible describes SAW as a choice
young man and a goodly there was not
among the children of Israel a goodly
irr person than he from his shoulders
and upward he was higher than any of the
people this Saul was anointed to be the
first king of Israel but if you know the
story of Saul you know that Saul
eventually goes from being a good King
to being a
bad King and this is the start of a long
line of Kings in Israel that for the
most part turned away from God lesson
number one when you turn away from God
to seek your own way it's going to lead
to destruction because this is what ends
up happening with Israel in second
chronicles chapter 36 verse 14 notice
we're working our way we went back to
Samuel we're now in second chronicles
chapter 36 a verse 14 listen to what the
Bible says here moreover all the chief
of the priests and of the people
transgressed or and the people
transgressed very much after all the
abominations of the heathen and polluted
the house of the Lord which he had
hallowed in Jerusalem and the Lord God
of their fathers sent to them by his
messengers rising up returns and sending
because he had compassion on his people
and on his dwelling place but they
marked the messengers of God and
despised his words and misused his
prophets until the wrath of the Lord
rose against his people till there was
no remedy now notice verse 17 therefore
he brought upon them the king of the
Caddy's or the Babylonians who slew
their young men with the sword in the
house of their sanctuary and had no
compassion upon the young man or Maiden
old man or him that stood for age he
gave them all into his hand verse 18 and
all the vessels of the house of God
great and small and the treasures of the
house of the Lord and the treasures of
the King and of his princes all these he
brought to Babylon and they burnt the
house of God and break down the wall of
Jerusalem and burnt all the palaces
thereof with fire and destroyed the
goodly vessels thereof do you get the
history
when Nehemiah is asking how is Jerusalem
looking this is part of the context
remember God had delivered Jerusalem or
delivered Israel out of Egyptian
captivity had brought them into their
own land and in their own land they were
supposed to be protected from the enemy
but what do they end up doing they ended
up rejecting the priest for a king in
other words they wanted to do things
their own way and and and their first
King turned out to be what kind of a
king an evil king started out good was
anointed and became evil listen
carefully started out good was anointed
but became evil they rejected their
priest for a king who at first looked
good but then turned out to be evil and
as a and as a result Heavenly Father
help us as a result as a result of of
Israel asking for a king there then
became this long line of Kings not all
of them bad but many of them leading
Israel into more and more apostasy until
God allows Babylon to go to Jerusalem
and to destroy the city and to break
down the walls and to burn down their
gates now let me ask you a question what
is the purpose of against a gate the
purpose of a wall the purpose of a gate
is to protect so when God had had built
up Jerusalem and had had their walls
built in their gates this was to keep
the enemies out but as a result of their
rebellion towards God Babylon comes
destroys that the city destroys the
walls destroy the gates and the Bible
tells us that the children of Israel
were taken into
Babylonian captivity and if you've ever
studied ancient Babylon you know that
Babylon was itself guarded by two leaved
gates so I want you to watch what's
happening here the people of God left
the safety of God inside the gates of
God to go to the gates of the enemy the
gates of Babylon now
to understand that this story under Stan
and historically but there is something
deeper here you see Adam was created by
God and placed in a garden that happened
to have gates and Adam was to be to be
secured in this garden however we know
that Adam and Eve ended up doing
something who was their king god but but
someone else came into the picture
asking hey would you let me rule you let
me be your king now who was that person
who was that individual that Adam and
Eve ended up saying hey we would rather
you as our king than God as our king it
was Satan now what do you know about
singing he's a deceiver but did he start
out as a deceiver no the Bible says in
Ezekiel chapter 28 that Lucifer was an
anointed cherub that he was the best
angel of all the Angels ever created but
we're told that iniquity was found in
him Ezekiel 28 verse 14 thou art the
anointed cherub that covereth and I have
set thee so that was upon the holy
mountain of God I walked up and down in
the midst of the stones of fire verse 15
that was perfect in thy ways from the
day that I was created until Watts
iniquity was found in thee the Bible
tells us that Lucifer was anointed of
God I want you to watch the parallel
just as Israel rejected their priest for
a king who was anointed who started out
good but then became evil so Adam and
Eve in the Garden of Eden rejected their
king for another King who was anointed
who started out good but became evil as
a result of this
Adam and Eve were placed outside the
garden in fact in Genesis chapter 3
verse 24 the Bible says here so he drove
out the man and placed at the east of
the Garden of Eden cherubims and a
flaming sword which turned every way to
keep the way of the Tree of Life Adam
and Eve had been put out of the garden
out of the gates of Eden one of the
things I want you to see here is that
mankind as a result of their choosing
the wrong king were led into captivity
were led into slavery living life
outside the gates of God is to be a
prisoner to the enemy of God and this is
exactly what happens in the garden but
praise God because God did not leave us
as captives God did not leave us and say
you guys messed up too bad you're gonna
be slaves forever because if we come
back to this story this story of
Nehemiah we will see here that before
Nehemiah comes upon the scene God had
actually sent another man Isaiah chapter
45 verse 1 notice it with me Isaiah
chapter 45 verse 1 the Bible tells us
here thus say the Lord to his anointed
to Cyrus whose right hand I have Holden
to subdue nations before him I will lose
the lines of Kings to open before him
the two Watts leaved gates and the gates
shall not be shut I will go before thee
and make the crooked places straight and
I will break in pieces the gates of
brass and cut in sunder the bars of iron
see Cyrus was the first leader of the
medo-persian Empire and God says the
Bible says that Cyrus was called
especially of God to go and
set his captives free Cyrus the Anointed
One Cana reminds me of Jesus because
Jesus came to do that very same thing he
came to set us free and notice what
Cyrus did Cyrus in order to set us free
what did he have to do he had to open
the gates of Babylon you remember
nito Persia is the Kingdom that
overthrew Babylon and the way they did
it was they entered into the gates of
Babylon in order to set the captives of
Babylon free but Ivan listened to me
Jesus did not leave us to suffer in our
sins he came to this world to set up a
process of deliverance so that you and I
could go free in fact in the book of
Ezra chapter one verse one and and and
just follow me because we're coming back
to the story of Nehemiah and Ezra
chapter 1 verse 1 the Bible says now in
the first year of Cyrus king of Persia
that the word of the Lord by the mouth
of Jeremiah might be fulfilled the Lord
stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of
Persia that he made a proclamation
throughout all of his kingdom and put it
also in writing saying thus saith Cyrus
king of Persia the Lord God of heaven
has given me all the kings of the earth
and he has charged me to build him a
house at where Jerusalem which is in
Judah who is there among you of all his
people his God be with him and let him
go up to Jerusalem which is in Judah and
do what build the house of the Lord God
of Israel he is the God which is in
Jerusalem so watch this Cyrus did not
just set the people free so that they
can leave Babylon and go do what they
wanted to do he set them free so that
they could do what rebuild Cyrus set
them free so that they could rebuild so
that were really already
rebuild now let me ask you a question
how many of you have ever lived life in
a way that you have regretted and you
wish that you could rebuild this is what
Jesus does for us he says I've set you
free and I'm going to allow you to go
back to the old ways and and and go back
to to rebuild the things that you messed
up on before now what a gracious God
what a merciful God that would allow us
to rebuild our our our shortcomings and
our Falls and our mistakes from the past
so Cyrus sets the captives free and so
they go they go to Jerusalem and and and
and then a matter of years pass now
remember Nehemiah is in the medo-persian
Empire and in fact he is now a subject
under the king artaxerxes Cyrus is gone
off the scene Cyrus was the first king
of medo-persia we're now in the time of
artaxerxes and Nehemiah wants to know
how is the rebuilding process going
alright did you catch what we just did
alright this brings us right back to
meet Nehemiah chapter 1 remember
Nehemiah is is is asking one of his
fellow Israelites who has who he has
come running to he says hey how is the
rebuilding project in Jerusalem going
how are the people doing with rebuilding
that which with which they messed up on
how are they doing with the grace of God
because it was only the grace of God
that that set them free that led them
out of the gates of Babylon so that they
could rebuild what they had messed up
and you can imagine you know knowing
that God let his people go so they can
read they can rebuild you can imagine
the joy and excitement that Nehemiah the
anticipation hey what's the word with
Jerusalem how is it going how are you
doing since you gave your life to Christ
and and what things are going on like
tell me about it man what's hot and then
he hears well what does he hear come
let's look at it again Nehemiah chapter
1 Nehemiah chapter 1 what does he hear
Bible tells us this is what he hears
Nehemiah 1 verse 3 verse 2 verse 3 I'm
sorry verse 3 and they said unto me the
remnant that are left of the captivity
there in the province are in great
affliction and reproach the wall of
Jerusalem is broken down and the lot the
what everyone the what everyone the
gates thereof are burned with fire and
it came to pass when I heard these words
that I sat down and watts wet and
mourned certain days and fasted and
prayed before the God of heaven and I
said I beseech thee I beseech thee O
Lord God of heaven the great and
terrible God that keepeth covenant and
mercy for them that love him and observe
His commandments let thine ear now be
attentive and thine eyes open that vow
me has hear the prayer of thy servant
which I pray before thee now day in
might for the children of Israel thy
servants and confess the sins of the
children of Israel which we have sinned
against thee both I and my father's
house have sinned not me ask you a
question is Nehemiah a righteous man is
he a holy man notice how he prays notice
how he
when he's praying to the God of heaven
he does not say they have sinned
he says we have sinned and in doing that
it's as though he is taking the sins of
his people upon himself and I want you
to understand that point very carefully
beloved because who does that sound like
Jesus nehemiah
was bent over in sorrow and the Bible
tells us listen carefully the Bible
tells us in the book of Isaiah 53 verse
4 surely he has borne our griefs and
carried our sorrows yet we did esteem
him stricken smitten of God and
afflicted Jesus Christ was a man of
sorrows on our accounts beloved Jesus
sets us free and sometimes I wonder how
he must feel just as he looks down and
he sees the rebuilding process not going
so well
does Jesus cast us off no no no no no
never because check this out guys so
what you're about to see in a story of
Nehemiah you're about to see is what
Jesus does on behalf of his people when
they are desolate when they are in
trouble when they are downtrodden when
they are discouraged when the building
project that you were excited to start
kind of fades off and now you're like
how'd I get here
Bible tells us Nehemiah chapter 2
Nehemiah chapter 2 verse 1 it came to
pass in a month of Nisan in the 20th
year of artaxerxes the king that want
that wine was before him and I took up
that wine and gave it unto the king now
I had not before I had not before time
said in his presence wherefore the king
said unto me why is thy countenance
sad seeing thou art not sick this is
nothing else but sorrow of heart then I
was very so afraid and he and I said
unto the king let the king live forever
why should not my countenance be sad
when the city the place of my father's
supplicant lieth waste and the gates and
the what everyone the gates thereof are
once consumed with fire then the king
said unto me for what does thou make
request so I pray to the God of heaven
and I said unto the king if it please
the king and if thy servant have found
favor in thy sight that thou wouldest
send me stop wouldn t my ask send me
send me
my people are suffering the city is
broken down the rebuilding project is
not going as planned what do you want
Nehemiah send me you want to know why
Jesus came to this world because he saw
us in need in fact Jesus did not
consider think about this Nehemiah is a
cup bearer in the king's court that's a
pretty good place to be
there was a long there was a law that
you could not come before the King sat
in meet a person you could not stand
before the king sad it was a long so
that's why Nehemiah says when the king
said why are you sad that's why I am I
said I was sore afraid but check it out
he was willing to risk his life look I
don't care what the law is do you know
do you know that Jesus did not consider
heaven a place
to be while you and I were lost Jesus
could have stayed there in the courts
maleic well you know what man they're
messed up down here on earth but you
know what I have it good no no he says
what send me praise God praise God that
Jesus came to us in our time of need not
this hour because you got to understand
this beloved I want you to see this
carefully
going back to Nehemiah chapter 2
Nehemiah chapter 2 and I want you to
notice what the King says or what
Nehemiah says to the king so it says and
I said unto the king if it please the
king and if I service have fun have
found favor in thy sight that that was
send me unto Judah unto the city of my
father's Sepulchre that I may want so
why is he going there he's going to
build what is he going to build the
temple has already been built so what's
been broken down the walls and the gates
the walls and the what everyone gates
please follow along gates are designed
to protect people to protect the city
listen so he goes to build he wants to
build it and verse verse 6 says and the
king said unto me the Queen also sitting
by him for how long shall thy journey be
and well with when with our return so we
know that Nehemiah is going but he's
going to one return he's going to go
back from whence he came are you are you
understanding me Nehemiah says send me
and the expectation is that he's going
to watch return notice when withour
return so if it pleased the king to send
me I will set a time moreover I said
unto the king if it pleases the King let
letters be given to me or let let us be
given me to the governor's beyond the
river that they may convey me over
till I come on to Judah what is he
asking for here he's asking for
authority to go he's asking for
authority to go what else verse 8 and
let a letter onto Asaph the keeper of
the Kings Forest that he may give me a
timber to make beams for the gates of
the palace just pause for a second
so what's he asking for permission to go
and wood ok he's asked for two two
things permission to go and all I need
is wood all I need is wood all I need is
wood that's all he's asking for and the
purpose of the wood is for what to build
the gates to build the gates so the wood
was to be given him for the gates
this is powerful because we know that
when Jesus comes to this earth there is
one thing he uses to redeem mankind and
it is wood it is the cross of Calvary it
is a tree of life that's what he used to
redeem his people so Nehemiah chapter 2
verse 11 the Bible tells us here of
verse 11 so I came to Jerusalem and was
there three days and I arose in the
night and I and some few men with me
neither told I any man what my God had
put in my heart to do it Jerusalem
neither was there any beasts with me
save the beasts that I wrote upon and I
went out by night by the gate of the
valley even
before the dragon well and to the dung
port and viewed the walls of Jerusalem
which were broken down and the gates
thereof which were consumed with fire
then I went on to the gate of the
fountain and to the Kings pool but there
was no place for the beasts that was
under me to cos then I went up in the
night by the brook and viewed the wall
and turned back and entered by the gate
of the valley and so returned and the
rulers knew not whether I went or what I
did neither had I as yet told it to the
Jews nor to the priests nor to the
nobles nor to the rulers nor to the
wrested that did the work so in other
words Nehemiah girls on a secret mission
and no one knows what his purpose is
kinda reminds me of Jesus who came to
this earth and people did not know well
what are you doing here what what is
your mission what is it they did not
understand who he was but Jesus knew
what he wanted to accomplish so neo my
to verse 17 then said I unto them
talking now to the children of Israel
you see the distress we are in how
Jerusalem lieth ways and the gates
thereof are burned with fire come let us
build up the wall of Jerusalem that we
be no more a reproach how many of you
are tired of being a reproach when it
comes to your Christian witness and
character of Jesus Christ Jesus says
come let us build so that you will no
longer be a reproach he comes down and
says come let us build now I begin to
understand so when Jesus set me free
it's not so I can just go and do my own
thing when he set me free it's for the
purpose of what rebuilding the life that
he gave me and even when I mess up with
that rebuilding project he says look I'm
gonna come down and I'm personally going
to assist you I'm personally going to
lead out in this work of rebuilding your
life
praise God for God like that verse 18
then I told him the hand of my god which
was good upon me and also the Kings word
that he had spoken to me and they said
let us rise up and build so they
strengthened their hands for this good
work what does God want us to do what
does God want us to do
you don't look excited to rise up in do
you kind of remind me of the Jews right
now in their line yeah you know we've
been at this for like 15 years and you
know we just we started out gone wrong
but now we're just like you know God
says come on I'm coming down to do this
with you let us rise up and build Wow
well well amen well it will build real
bill God says let us us rise up and bill
in other words he wants us to he's
trying to strengthen our hands to
complete the work so what happens now so
the Bible tells us now now they're all
excited I want you to check this out
Nehemiah chapter 3 Nehemiah chapter 3
and this is the heart of the message
right here but let me check this out
Nehemiah chapter 3 verse 1 and we're
going to go through a bunch of verses
here rapidly so just follow me Nehemiah
3 verse 1 then Elijah Elisha the high
priest rose up with his brethren the
priests and they builded the sheep gate
they sanctified it and set up the doors
of it even unto the tower of Mayor they
sanctified it onto the Tower of hanayo
so Nehemiah chapter 3 verse 1 is where
the building project begins it's where
it what everyone it begins and what
listen carefully what is the first thing
that they rebuild but what everyone
Nishiki the sheep gate I want you to
think about this guys the first thing
that nehemiah directs them to fix is the
Sheep gate that was the gate where the
sheep's would come through that were to
be sacrificed in the temple the very
first thing in the rebuilding process in
the in the process to getting the city
secure Jana feeling in the process of
getting the city secure the first thing
that needs to be rebuilt is the Sheep
gates but there wasn't just one gate in
Jerusalem there were ten gates hold on
notice with me verse 3 verse 3 says but
the first gate or but the fish gate that
the sons of of Hasan i--i build who also
laid the beams thereof so not only was
there the Sheep gate but there was also
the the fish gate go with me to verse 6
moreover also V the lot the old gates go
with me to verse 13 verse 13 there was
the the valley gate all right go with me
to verse 14 there was the the dung gate
okay go with me to verse 15 but the gate
of the fountain okay go with me to verse
26 verse 26 the Bible says moreover the
the net the Nephilim's
dwelt in or fell on to the place over
against the the water gate okay so there
was a war negating verse 26 not water
gate as in but the water gate okay so
verse 28 verse 28 the Bible says from
above the the horse gate so there was
the horse gate verse 29 and after them
repaired that at the son of of aimer
over against his house after him also
repaired also shamaya the son of
that name
the keeper of the east gate so there was
the east gate and then finally in verse
or rather verse 31 the Bible said after
him repaired nelq I the Goldsmith son on
to the place of Nephi names and on to
the merchants over against the myth Cod
unto the going I'm sorry the gate myth
called to the going up of the corner and
between the going up of the corner unto
the sheep gate repaired the Goldsmith's
and the merchants so ten gates in all
ten and as Nehemiah begins to do this
work Nehemiah chapter four verse 1 the
Bible says but it came to pass when
sanballat heard that we builded the wall
he was wroth and took great indignation
and mob the Jews and spake before his
brethren and the army of samaria and
said what do these believe what do these
feeble jews will they fortify themselves
will they what
fortify listen as they are building
these ten gates repairing these how many
gates every one ten gates their enemies
are mocking them and saying are you guys
trying to fortify yourselves notice what
the enemy asks are you trying to fortify
yourself now let me ask you a question
how many of you would like to fortify
yourself how many of you would like to
get some Teflon how many of you would
like to have it be so that the enemy
cannot penetrate your life do you think
these ten gates might have something to
do with that do you think that they were
named that just coincidentally or do you
think God is trying to show us something
about listen how I protect Jerusalem is
how I will protect you listen listen so
they're trying to they're trying to mock
the people that say look you're not
gonna do you can't do this
you're nobody you can't finish these
gates you're not going to be protected
and they're trying everything they can
they can to get into the heads
of the Jews want you to listen carefully
because why would Satan seek to stop the
rebuilding of the walls and the gates
why why would he do that listen
carefully because the Jews knew that the
finishing of Jerusalem played a major
prophetic role in the coming of the
Messiah did you catch that if you go
back to Daniel chapter 9 remember the
prophecy seventy weeks are determined
upon thy people you and then it says um
in fact let's read it let's read it
let's just read verse Daniel 9 verse 25
Stephen get up on the screen Daniel 9
verse 25 remember this is years before
Nehemiah and artaxerxes this prophecy
was written in the time of the
Babylonian Empire and it says here know
therefore and understand that from the
going forth of the commandment to
restore and to build Jerusalem unto the
Messiah the Prince shall be seven weeks
and threescore and two weeks don't worry
about all that but just focus on this
this street shall be built again and the
wall even in troublous times in other
words the prophecy stated that when
Jerusalem was completed something about
the rebuilding of Jerusalem and the
securing of the city would play a role
in the coming of the Messiah
so Satan knows if he can discourage the
people of God from finishing the work he
can delay or in his mind
just stop the coming of Jesus all
together so let me get into your mind
let me play let me let me let me let me
intimidate you anyone know what the haka
is you ever seen the haka okay so if you
if you watch any sports
in Australia they have a team call is it
Australia or New Zealand New Zealand got
a team called the All Blacks and if
you've ever seen the ritual that they do
before they play and this is what all
the teams do they do this I'm not gonna
do it here because I don't know how to
do it so go pass about to the haka no
but they do this thing it's this dance
where they're like screaming at the top
of them you know what I'm talking about
now they're like yelling and making all
kinds of ugly faces and the purpose is
to intimidate the enemy so beloved Satan
has a haka for you and he will do
everything he can to intimidate you to
stop you from doing the work that Jesus
has called you to do because he knows
that if you complete the work that plays
an important part in the second coming
of Jesus Christ so he wants to try to
stop you from doing the work but never
listen to me the prophet Daniel was told
that the streets and the wall would be
rebuilt in trouble at times these are
the trumpet sounds he was talking about
the enemies coming at the people of God
and saying you can't do this and who's
giving you permission and trying
everything in their power to stop the
work a beloved praise God Nehemiah was
at the forefront of the work you see
because these ten gates reflect the very
work that Christ came to do when he was
upon the earth these ten gates reflect
the mission of Christ in keeping his
people in surrounding his people look
what was the first game
it was a sheep gate did Jesus say I am
The Good Shepherd did Jesus say I am the
door to the sheepfold
and that no one can come to the Father
but through him that sheep gate beloved
the very first thing to be repaired
was to focus the mind on Jesus Christ as
the door to salvation not only that the
sheep gate reflect the work of Christ as
a shepherd but the fish gate reflects
his work as a Fisher of men
jesus said listen I'm gonna come I'm
gonna be a Fisher of men remember when
he took the disciples out on the Bundy
said casting your net there like we've
been fishing all trust me casting in
your net and when they cast in their net
they pulled up so many fish that the net
almost break jesus says listen I'm
coming up only to be a shepherd of your
souls but I'm coming to make you fishers
of men I am in fact the Fisher of men
the fish gate was to point to him in his
work of salvation on our behalf the old
gate Jesus came to re-establish the old
paths because the the disciples or the
the leaders of Israel had gone to the
place where he started teaching the
traditions of men in place of the
commandments of God the Bible tells us
in Jeremiah 6 verse 16 thus saith the
LORD standing in the way and see and ask
for the old what as for the what
everyone asks for the old paths where in
is the good way and walk therein and you
shall find rest for your souls did Jesus
say come unto me all ye that Labour and
are heavy laden and I will give you rest
Jesus not only represented the Sheep
gate
he not only represented the fish gate he
not only represented the old gate but
beloved even the valley gate because you
know what a valley represents in
Scripture right the valley represents
trial and tribulation remember Psalm 23
yea though I walk through the valley of
the shadow of death and
Jesus went through that Valley on our
behalf and beloved because he went
through that Valley on our behalf he
saved us from the valley of death so we
can say yea though I walk through the
valley of death I will fear no evil the
dung gate you wanna know the tongue gate
is you know what the dung gate is the
dung gate is where they threw all the
refuse from Israel from Jerusalem that's
the gate in which they took all the
garbage they took it to a place called
the valley of Gehenna it's a place where
not only garbage was burned but the
bodies of the poor were disposed and if
the word Gehenna rings a bell to you it
is because that is a word that is used
to describe Hell and beloved Jesus
tasted death for every one of us that we
might be saved from becoming dung that
we might be saved from becoming refuse
that we might be saved
from becoming garbage so Jesus not only
ministered to us through that
symbolically through the through the
dung gate but he's also the fountain
gate because Jesus said in Revelation 21
verse 6 I am Alpha and Omega the
beginning and the ending I will give
unto him that is athirst of the fountain
of the water of life freely Jesus says
come unto me you that are thirsty he is
the Fountain Gate beloved not only does
he represent the fountain gate but he is
the water gate because the difference
between the fountain gate and the water
gate is a fountain gate you drink from
the water gate is where you are cleansed
and Jesus says I am the water of life
Ephesians 5:25 husband's love your wives
even as Christ also loved the church and
gave himself for it that he might
sanctify and cleanse it with the washing
of water by the word that he might
present it to himself a glorious church
not having spot or wrinkle or any such
thing but that it should be holy and
without blemish jesus is sacrificed on
the cross his mission reflects the work
of the water gate not the water gate
but the water Gaines beloved Jesus at
the the horse gate you say what does a
horse gate pastor what were horses used
for in the Old Testament they were used
for war they were used for battle and
the book of our Revelation chapter 19 11
it tells us this and I saw heaven opened
and behold a white horse and he that sat
upon it on him was called faithful and
true and in righteousness he doth judge
and make war Jesus came to war on our
behalf he said I will not leave you
alone I'm going to fight for you and
that is exactly what he does for us
beloved listen to me the east gate
you know what the east gate represents
because a Bible tells us that Jesus when
he comes he is coming from the east we
have something to look forward to and
that is the second coming of Christ and
finally but never listen to me carefully
finally that tenth gate that tenth gate
is the gate of judgment that's what the
Hebrew word means it looked like a weird
name that name symbolizes judgment and
beloved Jesus in John chapter 12 verse
32 said and I if I be lifted up will
draw all men unto me
he said now is the Prince of this world
judged the reason why Satan was trying
to stop Christ from accomplishing these
things is because he knew that if Christ
accomplished these things then the
people of God would be secure and
surrounded listen to me carefully guys
the Bible says that it took Nehemiah
this is powerful Nehemiah is doing this
work and the enemies are coming at him
saying come there there they go from
mocking to inviting him to come down
from the wall you remember that come
down come down come down from Nehemiah
wasn't an exalted at a place
a high place doing a work of redemption
I don't know if you caught that he was
in an exalted place an elevated place
doing the work of redemption and they
tried to get him to come down from the
cross I mean the wall come down and near
my said no I cannot come down because I
am doing a great work but loving it was
wood that provided security for all of
those gates the Bible tells us that it
took Nehemiah 52 days to complete the
games 52 days
Nehemiah say I will not come down I'm
doing a great work and 52 days later
Jerusalem is surrounded by a wall and
gates you realize that if you take 52
days from the time that Jesus was up on
a cross saying I will not come down
because I'm doing a great work 52 days
later is the day of Pentecost and what
happened on the day of Pentecost beloved
is that fire fell on Jerusalem on God's
people and you need to see this because
zechariah chapter 25 says this for I say
the Lord will be unto her that is
Jerusalem a wall of fire roundabout wait
I don't know if you caught that just now
what fell on the day of Pentecost fire
you want to know what that fire was it
was the Holy Spirit Zechariah says I
will be a wall of fire around Jerusalem
beloved 52 days after Christ went up on
the cross to complete the work of
building the wall and the gates 52 days
later a wall of fire surrounds his
church now listen carefully guys
when Nehemiah finished the work you have
to see this Nehemiah chapter xvii
Nehemiah chapter 7 we are almost
finished guys but please follow along
Nehemiah chapter 7 verse 1 now it came
to pass when the wall was built and I
had set up the doors and the porters and
the singers and the Levites were
appointed that I gave my brother Hanna
and I at Hanna Meyer the ruler of the
palace charged over Jerusalem for he was
a faithful man and feared God above many
and I said unto them let not the gates
of Jerusalem be opened until the Sun be
hot and while they stand by let them
shut let them shut the doors and bar
them and appoint watches of the
inhabitants of Jerusalem everyone in his
watch and everyone to be over against
his house so Nehemiah knows it's time
for him to go back and so what does he
do he says set watch over the work I
completed okay I need you to watch to
guard you don't need to build I just
need you to watch and take care of that
which I let out in what does that mean
for us Church Jesus says I've appointed
you as Watchmen watch your gates guys
because gates are designed to protect
and to keep out the enemy and we're not
talking about steel gates we're talking
about wooden gates we're talking about
cross of Calvary that's the gate those
are the gates that's the wall that we
need to build around us that is what's
going to keep out spiritual enemies god
says watch take care of the work that I
have accomplished in you not you
yourselves you didn't do it I let out in
this work now all I'm asking you to do
is watch the games that's it if you
watch the gates everything is going to
be good watch what I have left for you
guard your connection with the holy
spirit and listen you when you do this
you're gonna have to do it in trouble US
times the enemy is gonna come at you and
he's gonna try to find a way to weaken
you at the Sheep games did you get what
I just said he's going to try to get you
to lose your trust in what Jesus
accomplished for you at the cross or he
might attack you about the fish gate
come on man win souls you you don't know
the Bible you don't know how to witness
you don't know how to share come on it
doesn't matter what gate he will try to
attack you at one of those gates the
valley gate man this is too hard
this is too tough I give up I'm throwing
in the towel guard the gates because
beloved when we guard the gates we
realize that Satan can have no access
none what so ever
Nehemiah told him do not open the gates
in the dark only open the gates to the
light and that's what
a neutron he tries to enter in through
doubt through discouragement through
depression God's Nehemiah said only
opened the gates when the Sun is hot
right he didn't say like at dawn no no
no no no when the Sun is hot
only let light in do not let the
darkness in I will share with you one
more thought and then we'll close the
church is here because of these gates we
are here today because those before us
have guarded the gates and I need you to
understand where we are prophetically
in these gates you see listen the first
three gates check this out very very
quickly the first three gates this is in
order if you were to get a map of
Jerusalem old old Jerusalem you will see
that the gates were actually in order
around the city and they were actually
peered the first three gates then the
then the middle four gates and then the
last three days right there so they were
all in a circle around Jerusalem and I
wanted to fix up the first three gates
the Sheep gate the fish gate and the old
gate you know if we looked at those
gates you know we would see we would see
the early church the Sheep gate the
sacrifice of Christ the fish gate where
multitudes came in Pentecost and the old
where the church was founded upon the
old paths and the old ways those are the
first three gates you know what gates
come next the valley gates what do we
say the valley gate represented trial
and persecution let me ask you was there
a period of time that the church began
to be persecuted by the Roman power and
Valley gate turns into dumb game because
the rubbish of traditions and false
worship began to come into the church
during the Dark Ages but praise God for
fountain gate
because that's where the Reformation
started to realize wait a minute
these things are rubbish and we've got a
critter sway and return to the fountain
the true and living water which turns
into the water gate which represents
which represents cleansing and
purification and beloved you look at
that whole process Valley gate to dung
gate to fountain gate to water gate it's
the whole Protestant Reformation ending
or concluding with God's endtime
movements then comes horse cane because
remember love is that's the battle the
devil was angry with the remnant and
went to make what's war with the remnant
of his people but praise God for
Eastgate cuz we know that an angel will
descend from the east having the seal of
the Living God and he will seal his
people before the time of the end and
beloved judgment gate judgment gate
closes it all off because when the
judgment is over Jesus Christ will come
again so listen we are here because the
early church took care of sheep gate and
fish gate and and at an old path gate
and the middle aged church took care of
alligator and dung gate and fountain
gate and water gate and now it's up to
us beloved horse can't you understand
the language I'm speaking to you in it's
not up to us to make sure that we are
ready to stand strong in battle to take
up our armor to God on our armor on and
fight for the Lord it's up to us to make
sure that each gate is completed with
the sealing of God's people and that
sealing message going forward and it's
up to us to make sure that the judgment
gate is finished revelation 14:6 fear
God and give glory to him for the hour
of his judgment it's come but no but as
Megan comes forward to pray Megan where
are you
she's coming forward to pray and she
comes forward beloved listen to me who
many of us have a lot have allowed the
darkness of night into our gates
Jesus said listen I came to provide wood
for your gates the enemy will not be
able to penetrate the cross let the
cross be before every one of your gates
and I guarantee you the enemy will not
be able to penetrate it not with
darkness not with doubt not with fear
and so today today you are saying to
yourself Lord that's it
I'm tired of leaving my gates unguarded
I'm going to stand today to demonstrate
to you to show you and to ask you into
my heart so that you your cross can be
the guard at every one of these gates
help me Lord to guard these gates Lord
surround me surround me that's right as
I'm going to ask you to stand to your
feet Lord surround me
I'm tired of letting the enemy in
through my gates I'm tired of being like
a city without walls that can just sing
can come in and do as he pleases and
then leave when he wants to and come
back when he wants to lord help me only
to let light in through my gates
meagan lead us in prayer